Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to be
learning how to read a chemical formula.
More specifically, we're going to
learn how to count the number of
atoms you have within the different
compounds you find in these formulas.
So, what is this all about?
What do we know so far?
Well, the first thing is that we know
is that atoms make up all matter.
And that atoms are made up of different
subatomic particles, which is leading
to them bonding together because they
want and desire all these different
numbers of electrons in order to
try to achieve the octet rule.
However, uh, most of the, most matter that
we see do not really exist just as atoms.
As we're starting to realize,
most of matter that you see around
you is in the form of compounds.
Uh, whether it's maybe like the
different materials that make up your
phone or the screen on it, the, your,
maybe your laptop keys, the walls of
your home, uh, the, maybe the desk
that you're sitting at your bed, all
these things are made up of compounds.
This is the majority of things
that exist in our world.
Uh, so what we're gonna try to
do is learn how we can count them
here and try to understand basic
concepts in this fundamental video.
Let's take a look.
The first thing about chemical formulas is
that they can have the following things.
So the first one is that they will
have the element symbols that you
can find on your periodic table.
Now, this is one of the reasons it's
very important that you start, you
are memorizing your periodic table.
It makes it easier to do your
general chemistry course.
Um, even some classes don't even
give you the complete information.
It fully depends on what, who your
teacher is, what they're giving you.
Need to know those symbols.
As a general rule of thumb for me and
my students, I recommend the first
20, know the symbols, know your names,
because they are some of the most
common that we have in our world.
Um, after that, we're going
to be using subscripts.
So what exactly is a subscript?
So if I have, let's say, water right
here, H2O, a subscript is a number
that's written as like a lower font.
Um, so this is what we
refer to as a subscript.
Uh, so what subscripts are for
are telling you the number of
atoms that are in this molecule.
So for this one, this is letting
you know that you have two
hydrogen atoms that are here.
Okay, so we have two hydrogens.
Um, so that is a very important piece of
information for when we say we have water.
Thank you.
here.
Sometimes you'll also see the
use of parentheses as well.
Now we'll talk about them more in
detail soon, but they're usually used
to group certain, uh, polyatomics
or formula units together.
So that way you are, you are counting
and balancing your charges correctly.
Okay.
It's very important that when
something's in parentheses, They stay
together, they belong together, okay?
Just letting you know how many units
of that particular molecule you have.
Okay, so for this particular one, you
can see that you have two hydrogens,
and then we have a single oxygen in H2O.
So what about the subscript
that is over here for oxygen?
Notice that it's currently vacant.
So what that means is
that there is a one here.
So it is telling you that
there's only one element.
Generally, we leave it blank.
But depending on how you are being
graded on different assessments, you
might have to put the number one there.
Um, especially if it's something
that's more of an auto graded response.
But that means there's one single oxygen.
So let's write that down.
Alright, let's go on to our next part, so
that way we can learn a little bit more
of these different chemical formulas.
Alright, so I have magnesium
hydroxide here written for us, and
we are going to go through what the
general rule is for parentheses.
So how exactly do they work?
Well, what the first thing we are
looking for is our subscripts.
One thing you can notice right away, there
is no subscript written next to magnesium.
So what can we exactly say about that?
Is that Mg, there is one
atom of Mg here, right?
So one atom of magnesium.
Now, what about the parentheses here?
How does this work?
Well, the general idea here is that this 2
is going to be distributed to each of the
individual elements within, meaning it's
multiplying each one of those elements.
So being that each one of these
has a little box next to them,
remember, they're just one.
So in a sense, the way that this
works is if I have oxygen here, you
are essentially taking one times, uh,
two in this case, which is telling
you, hey, you have two oxygen atoms.
And that's the same thing
for hydrogen, right?
We can, we do two times one and we
can see that we have two hydrogen
atoms within magnesium hydroxide.
So when we're trying to understand
this general rule here, when you're
counting the number of atoms, first
you got to count how parentheses.
So as you saw with oxygen and hydrogen
above, I counted one within each of them.
Now most of the time when you have
parentheses, you generally have a number
outside, meaning an additional subscript.
So this is going to be used
to multiply what's within.
So what do I mean by that?
Let's just do a very, very hypothetical
example like the one that is here.
So what are we going to do?
Let's count these numbers and letters
for A, B, and C, these fake elements.
How would it work?
The first thing I want to do is let's
just count the number of A elements.
And what you can see is, is
that, oh, we got a W here.
It's not in parentheses.
So what that tells you is that A is
equal to, uh, W amount of atoms, right?
So W atoms.
What about B?
Okay, so B has the subscript of
X next to it, but notice that
it's inside of these parentheses.
So how does that exactly work?
The is going to distribute itself.
to both of these species.
Now, when we are writing
formulas, you do not carry this
out like a normal math problem.
We're just using this to count the number
of atoms, so you know how many there are.
We leave it in its formula, okay?
So it's there, it's in that format
for a reason, because it's letting you
know the different units that exist.
But when we're counting atoms, all's
we're doing is taking x times z, and
that's telling you however many atoms
you have, okay, so that's the number.
Now when it comes to c, same idea,
right, we're gonna take y times z,
and you'll have that many atoms.
Let's take a look at a real
one so that maybe it'll help
make a little bit more sense.
Let's take a look.
Okay, so in this example, we are
going to be counting how many of
each atom exist within a formula.
So this is very similar to the
alphabetical one we had earlier.
So what are we going to be doing first?
Well, we got to realize we have a
bunch of different subscripts here.
So let's first start with iron.
We can see iron's
outside of the subscript.
There's nothing written there.
So we can automatically assume
we have one atom of iron.
Now, what else do we have?
Well, let's take a look.
So if we look at nitrogen
next, we see that there's a,
there's nothing written there.
So once again, it's a one.
So how is that going to work?
Well, we have a two outside of it.
So what we will do here is we'll
simply take that 2, times that by
1, and we have a total of 2 atoms
of nitrogen within this compound.
Now with, uh, with oxygen,
we have a 3 inside.
We're going to multiply that as well,
so 3 times 2, and that lets you know,
hey, you have 6 atoms of oxygen.
Now, just to kind of illustrate, what
does this, what does this represent?
Remember, ionic compounds exist
in a lattice type of network.
So what this is kind of letting you
know is that, hey, we have this Iron
2 plus that's here, and there are
different nitrate units on each side.
So it's kind of like we have,
let's say, an NO3 on one side.
NO3 on the other.
And they are being, they're
surrounding this iron and it's
in a repeating framework, okay?
So there's many of these in a row.
And notice how I'm keeping NO3s together.
That's the important part.
The parentheses keep them together.
You do not carry it out
like in math operation.
Um, generally the way you will see these
is how it was originally presented.
Let's take a look at our next one.
So our next one here is essentially
we have calcium arsenate.
So calcium arsenate is the same idea.
So we're going to be counting all
these different species that we have.
So we notice there's some subscripts here.
So the first one was for calcium.
We have three atoms of calcium.
Now we have once again our parentheses,
we have a two outside of that.
So we're going to be distributing it
to all the different species within.
The first one is Arsenate, which
only has a one next to it, and
we're going to multiply that by two.
Oxygen has a four next to it, and
we're also gonna multiply that by two.
And so we have two Arsenate.
atoms and then eight oxygen
atoms in this compound.
So this is the whole idea of when
we're looking at compounds and
molecules, this is how we can count
them for chemical formulas and
be able to read them correctly.
Thank you so much for watching.
I hope that this video helped you
understand chemical formulas a
little bit better for the future.
And please, if you have not already,
hit that like and subscribe button.
Keep, please keep, help support
this channel so we can spread
more chemistry to more students.
And I hope to see you all in the future.
Bye now.